Images like this, from the Auschwitz concentration camp,
صور مثل هذه , من معتقل أٌسشوتز ,
have been seared into our consciousness during the twentieth century
إنطبعت في أذهاننا خلال القرن العشرين
and have given us a new understanding of who we are,
و أعطتنا مفهوم جديد لتعريفنا بمن نحن
where we've come from and the times we live in.
من أين أتينا و الزمن الذي نعيش فيه اليوم .
During the twentieth century, we witnessed the atrocities
خلال القرن العشرين , كنا شهود على وحشية
of Stalin, Hitler, Mao, Pol Pot, Rwanda and other genocides,
كل من ستالين , هتلر , ماو , بول بوت , رواندا و غيرها من إبادات جماعية
and even though the twenty-first century is only seven years old,
و بالرغم من أنه قد مضت سبعة سنوات فقط على القرن الواحد و عشرين ,
we have already witnessed an ongoing genocide in Darfur
شهدنا بالفعل إبادات جماعية مستمره في دارفور
and the daily horrors of Iraq.
و رعب يومي في العراق .
This has led to a common understanding of our situation,
و هذا قد دلنا إلى مفهوم عام لوضعنا الحالي ,
namely that modernity has brought us terrible violence, and perhaps
أعني : إن العصر الحديث جاء لنا بعنف فظيع , وربما
that native peoples lived in a state of harmony that we have departed from, to our peril.
حتى السكان الأصليين الذين كانوا يعيشون في انسجام معا رحلنا منه إلى واقعنا الخطير .
Here is an example
إليكم مثال على ذلك .
from an op-ed on Thanksgiving, in the Boston Globe
من عناوين عدد يوم عيد الشكر في جريدة بوسطن العالمية
a couple of years ago, where the writer wrote, "The Indian life
قبل عامين مضت , عندما كتب الكاتب "حياة الهنود
was a difficult one, but there were no employment problems,
كانت صعبة , لكن لم توجد لديهم مشاكل توظيف ,
community harmony was strong, substance abuse unknown,
كان تناغم المجتمع قوي , و لم يعرف وقتها إدمان المخدرات ,
crime nearly non-existent, what warfare there was between tribes
الجريمة تقريبا لم تكن موجودة , الصراع آنذاك بين القبائل
was largely ritualistic and seldom resulted in indiscriminate
كان واسع النطاق فيما بينهم و نادراً ما يؤدي إلي أضرار عشوائية
or wholesale slaughter." Now, you're all familiar with this treacle.
أو الذبح الجماعي ." الأن , معروف لكم كلكم هذه السائل اللزج المولاس .
We teach it to our children. We hear it on television
نعلمها لأطفالنا , و نسمعها في التلفاز
and in storybooks. Now, the original title of this session
و في الكتب القصصية . الآن , العنوان الأصلي لهذه الفقرة
was, "Everything You Know Is Wrong," and I'm going to present evidence
كان , " كل معلوماتنا كانت خطأ " و أنا سأوضح لكم الدليل
that this particular part of our common understanding is wrong,
على أن هذا الجزء الخاص بالإعتقاد السائد بيننا هو خاطيء :
that, in fact, our ancestors were far more violent than we are,
و الواقع أن أجدادنا كانوا أكثر عنفاً بكثير منا اليوم ,
that violence has been in decline for long stretches of time,
والعنف يقل بكثير على مدى الزمان
and that today we are probably living in the most peaceful time in our species' existence.
و ربما نحن نعيش اليوم في أقصى درجات السلام في تاريخ تواجد البشرية .
Now, in the decade of Darfur and Iraq,
الآن , في زمن دارفور و العراق ,
a statement like that might seem somewhere between hallucinatory
جملة مثل تلك قد تبدو ما بين الهلوسة
and obscene. But I'm going to try to convince you
واللامعقولية . لكني سأحاول إقناعكم
that that is the correct picture. The decline of violence
إن هذه هي الصورة الحقيقية . إن هبوط مستوى العنف
is a fractal phenomenon. You can see it over millennia,
ظاهرة جذرية متوالية . تستطيع أن تراها عبر آلاف السنين
over centuries, over decades and over years,
عبر قرون , عبر عقود , وعبر السنوات
although there seems to have been a tipping point at the onset
على الرغم من وجود نقطة ذروة لبعض اللحظات المؤثرة في
of the Age of Reason in the sixteenth century. One sees it
عصر التنوير في القرن السادس عشر . واحد يراها
all over the world, although not homogeneously.
في كل أنحاء العالم , على الرغم من إنها ليست بنفس التشابه .
It's especially evident in the West, beginning with England
إنها دليل خاص في الغرب , إبتداء من إنجلترا
and Holland around the time of the Enlightenment.
وهولندا تقريباً في عصر التنوير .
Let me take you on a journey of several powers of 10 --
دعني آخذكم في رحلة مكونة من مستويات متعددة من القوة من 10 --
from the millennium scale to the year scale --
من مقياس الألفية إلى مقياس السنة --
to try to persuade you of this. Until 10,000 years ago, all humans
لأحاول إقناعكم بهذا . حتى 10,000 سنة مضت , كل البشر
lived as hunter-gatherers, without permanent settlements
عاشوا في حالة صيد مستمرة بدون وجود إستقرار دائم
or government. And this is the state that's commonly thought
أو وجود حكومات . و هذه هي الفترة التي يٌظن فيها
to be one of primordial harmony. But the archaeologist
إنها واحدة من السلام البدائي . لكن عالم الآثار
Lawrence Keeley, looking at casualty rates
لورانس كيلي , بالنظر إلى معدلات الضحايا
among contemporary hunter-gatherers, which is our best source
في زمن حياة الصيد القديمة - و التي تعتبر أفضل مصدر
of evidence about this way of life, has shown a rather different conclusion.
للدلالة على نظام الحياة آنذاك -- تَبين لنا نتيجة مختلفة إلى حد ما .
Here is a graph that he put together
هذا رسم بياني وضعه معا يوضح
showing the percentage of male deaths due to warfare
و يبين نسبة وفيات الرجال بسبب القتال
in a number of foraging, or hunting and gathering societies.
على سرقة المؤن أو الصيد و في تجميع الجماعات
The red bars correspond to the likelihood that a man will die
الخطوط الحمراء تتوافق مع إحتمالية موت الرجل
at the hands of another man, as opposed to passing away
على يد رجل آخر , مقابل أن يموت وحده
of natural causes, in a variety of foraging societies
بسبب الموت الطبيعي , في المجتمعات المتنوعة الرحالة
in the New Guinea Highlands and the Amazon Rainforest.
في مرتفعات نيوغينيا و في غابات الأمازون .
And they range from a rate of almost a 60 percent chance that a man will die
ويصل الإحتمال إلى نسبة تقريبية 60% أن الرجل سوف يموت
at the hands of another man to, in the case of the Gebusi,
على أيدي رجل آخر , مقارنة في حالة جيبوسي ,
only a 15 percent chance. The tiny, little blue bar in the lower
فقط فرصة 15% . الخط الصغير جدا الأزرق بالأسفل
left-hand corner plots the corresponding statistic from United States
على الزاوية اليسار يوضح إحصائية من الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
and Europe in the twentieth century, and includes all the deaths
و أوروبا في القرن العشرين , و تتضمن كل الوفيات
of both World Wars. If the death rate in tribal warfare had prevailed
في الحربين العالميتين . إذا كان معدل الوفيات في صراعات القبائل هو الذي ساد
during the 20th century, there would have been two billion deaths rather than 100 million.
خلال القرن العشرين , كان سيكون هناك 2 بليون حالة وفاة مقارنة مع 100 مليون .
Also at the millennium scale, we can look
حتى في النظر إلى منظور الألفية , نستطيع أن نرى
at the way of life of early civilizations such as the ones described
طريقة الحياة في بداية الحضارة كالتي تم وصفها
in the Bible. And in this supposed source of our moral values,
في الكتاب المقدس . وفي هذا المفترض أن يكون مصدر من مصادر قيمنا الأخلاقية .
one can read descriptions of what was expected in warfare,
يستطيع أي أحد أن يقرأ أوصاف ماذا كان يتٌوقع من الحروب ,
such as the following from Numbers 31: "And they warred
مثل المثال التالي من إنجيل العدد , أصحاح 31 : "و هم حاربوا
against the Midianites as the Lord commanded Moses,
ضد المديانيين كما أمر الرب موسى ,
and they slew all the males. And Moses said unto them,
و ذبحوا كل الذكور . و موسى قال لهم ,
'Have you saved all the women alive? Now, therefore, kill every male
"هل أبقيتم كل أنثي حية ؟ الآن , إذبحوا كل ذكر
among the little ones and kill every woman that hath known man
من هؤلاء الصغار و إقتلوا كل إمرأة عرفت رجل
by lying with him, but all the women children that have not know a man
بالمضاجعه , لكن كل أطفال النساء اللاتي لم تعرفن رجل
by lying with him keep alive for yourselves.'" In other words,
بالمضاجعه إبقوهم أحياء لكم " أي في عبارة أخرى ,
kill the men; kill the children; if you see any virgins,
إذبحوا كل الرجال , إذبحوا كل الأطفال , و إذا رأيتم أي عذارى
then you can keep them alive so that you can rape them.
تستطيعون أن تحتفظوا بهن للإغتصاب .
You can find four or five passages in the Bible of this ilk.
تستطيعون أن تجدوا أربعة أو خمسة مواضع في الكتاب المقدس على هذا النحو .
Also in the Bible, one sees that the death penalty
أيضا في الكتاب المقدس أي شخص ما يري بأن عقوبة الإعدام
was the accepted punishment for crimes such as homosexuality,
كانت تقبل كعقوبة لجرائم مثل المثلية الجنسية ,
adultery, blasphemy, idolatry, talking back to your parents --
الزنا , الكفر, الوثنية , التحدث إلى والديك بوقاحه --
(Laughter) -- and picking up sticks on the Sabbath.
(ضحك ) -- و حمل العصي في أيام السبت .
Well, let's click the zoom lens
حسناً , دعنا نرى الموضوع عن قرب أكثر
down one order of magnitude, and look at the century scale.
و نشاهد من منظور رقمي ماذا حدث خلال القرن .
Although we don't have statistics for warfare throughout
على الرغم من إننا لا نملك إحصائيات عن الحروب خلال
the Middle Ages to modern times,
الفترة من العصور الوسطى إلى الزمن الحديث ,
we know just from conventional history -- the evidence
إلا إننا نعرف من التاريخ التقليدي -- الدليل
was under our nose all along that there has been a reduction
كان تحت أنوفنا بأن هناك تناقص
in socially sanctioned forms of violence.
في صور العقوبات الإجتماعية بأشكال عنيفة .
For example, any social history will reveal that mutilation and torture
على سبيل المثال , أي مجتمع في التاريخ سيكشف بأن البتر و التعذيب
were routine forms of criminal punishment. The kind of infraction
كان شكل روتيني لعقوبات المجرمين . إذا فعلت مخالفة
today that would give you a fine, in those days would result in
اليوم كنت ستحصل على غرامة , في تلك الأيام هذه المخالفة ستكون نتيجتها هي
your tongue being cut out, your ears being cut off, you being blinded,
قطع لسانك , قطع إذنك , جعلك تصاب بالعمى ,
a hand being chopped off and so on.
قطع يدك و هكذا دواليك .
There were numerous ingenious forms of sadistic capital punishment:
كانت هناك طرق مبتكرة من السادية لتنفيذ عقوبة الإعدام :
burning at the stake, disemboweling, breaking on the wheel,
الحرق علي خازوق , نزع الأحشاء , كسر الجسد عن طريق العجلة
being pulled apart by horses and so on.
التي تسحبك بإتجاهين مختلفين من خلال الأحصنة .. و هكذا .
The death penalty was a sanction for a long list of non-violent crimes:
عقوبة الإعدام كانت عقوبة لقائمة طويلة من الجرائم التي لا تصنف علي أنها جرائم عنف :
criticizing the king, stealing a loaf of bread. Slavery, of course,
نقد الملك , سرقة الخبز . العبودية , بالطبع ,
was the preferred labor-saving device, and cruelty was
كانت الشيء المفضل لتقليص نفقات العمل , و الأعمال الوحشية كانت
a popular form of entertainment. Perhaps the most vivid example
متعة كبيرة معروفة آنذاك . لربما كان أكثر مثال يوضح الأعمال الوحشية الحية
was the practice of cat burning, in which a cat was hoisted
هو حرق القطط وهي حية , من خلال تعليق القط
on a stage and lowered in a sling into a fire,
في قفص و يتم إنزاله في النار ,
and the spectators shrieked in laughter as the cat, howling in pain,
و كانت تتعالى ضحكات المتفرجين وقتها عندما يبدأ القط , بالصراخ من الألم ,
was burned to death.
من الحرق حتي الموت .
What about one-on-one murder? Well, there, there are good statistics,
و ماذا عن القتل من شخص لآخر ؟ حسنا , هناك إحصائيات جيدة ,
because many municipalities recorded the cause of death.
لأن الكثير من المحليات سجلت سبب الوفاة .
The criminologist Manuel Eisner
عالم الجريمة مانيول إسنير
scoured all of the historical records across Europe
رصد كل السجلات التاريخة عبر أوروبا
for homicide rates in any village, hamlet, town, county
لمعدلات القتل في أي قرية , واحة , بلدة , دولة
that he could find, and he supplemented them
كل ما إستطاع الوصول إليه , و قام بتزويدهم
with national data, when nations started keeping statistics.
بإحصائيات رسمية عنما قامت الشعوب بالعمل على حفظ الإحصائيات .
He plotted on a logarithmic scale, going from 100 deaths
وقد رسم علي مقياس لوغاريثمي , يبدأ من 100 حالة قتل
per 100,000 people per year, which was approximately the rate
لكل 100,000 شخص بالسنة , و الذي كان تقريبا معدل
of homicide in the Middle Ages. And the figure plummets down
المقتولين في العصور الوسطى . و الشكل بدأ بالهبوط
to less than one homicide per 100,000 people per year
إلى أقل من حالة قتل واحدة لكل 100,000 شخص بالسنة
in seven or eight European countries. Then, there is a slight uptick
في سبعة أو ثمان دول أوروبية . ثم صار هناك قفزة بسيطة
in the 1960s. The people who said that rock 'n' roll would lead
في الستينيات . الناس الذين قالوا بأن موسيقى الروك سوف تقود
to the decline of moral values actually had a grain of truth to that.
لإنحدار في القيم الأخلاقية أصابوا الحقيقة في ذلك .
But there was a decline from at least two orders of magnitude
لكن كان هناك إنحدار من على الأقل ترتيبين في معدلات
in homicide from the Middle Ages to the present,
القتل منذ العصور الوسطى إلى الحاضر ,
and the elbow occurred in the early sixteenth century.
و في القفزة التي حدثت في بداية القرن السادس عشر .
Let's click down now to the decade scale.
دعنا ننظر عن قرب إلى منظور العشر سنوات .
According to non-governmental organizations
بالرجوع إلى مؤسسات غير حكومية
that keep such statistics, since 1945, in Europe and the Americas,
والتي إحتفظت بالإحصاءات , منذ 1945 في أوروبا و أمريكا
there has been a steep decline in interstate wars,
كان هناك إنحدار كبير في الحروب المشتركة ,
in deadly ethnic riots or pogroms, and in military coups,
في أعمال الشغب العرقية المميته أو المذابح و في الإنقلابات العسكرية ,
even in South America. Worldwide, there's been a steep decline
حتى في أمريكا الجنوبية . كل أنحاء العالم , كان هناك إنحدار كبير
in deaths in interstate wars. The yellow bars here show the number
في القتلى في الحروب المشتركة . الخط الأصفر هنا يوضح عدد
of deaths per war per year from 1950 to the present.
القتلى لكل حرب منذ 1950 إلى حاضرنا اليوم .
And, as you can see, the death rate goes down from 65,000 deaths
وكما ترون , معدل الوفيات يهبط من 65,000 قتيل
per conflict per year in the 1950s to less than 2,000 deaths
لكل صراع في السنة الواحدة في الخمسينات إلى أقل من 2,000 قتيل
per conflict per year in this decade, as horrific as it is.
لكل صراع في السنة الواحدة في هذا العقد , على الرغم من إنها مروعة .
Even in the year scale, one can see a decline of violence.
حتى في منظور السنة يستطيع الواحد منا أن يرى هبوط في العنف .
Since the end of the Cold War, there have been fewer civil wars,
منذ نهاية الحرب الباردة كان هناك عدد أقل من الحروب الأهلية ,
fewer genocides -- indeed, a 90 percent reduction since post-World War II highs --
أقل إبادات جماعية -- في الحقيقة , هبوط 90% منذ نهاية الحرب العالية الثانية في أعلي مستوياتها --
and even a reversal of the 1960s uptick in homicide and violent crime.
و حتى في إرتداد الستينيات في حالات القتل و جرائم العنف .
This is from the FBI Uniform Crime Statistics. You can see
هذه وثيقة من الشرطة الفيدرالية توضح إحصائية الجرائم : تستطيعون أن تروا
that there is a fairly low rate of violence in the '50s and the '60s,
إن هناك نوعا ما معدل منخفض للعنف في الخمسينات و الستينات
then it soared upward for several decades, and began
ثم إنها إرتفعت لعقود عديدة و بدأت
a precipitous decline, starting in the 1990s, so that it went back
بهبوط كبير , بدأ من التسعينيات , و عادت كما كانت
to the level that was last enjoyed in 1960.
تقريبا إلى مستوى ما قبل الستينيات
President Clinton, if you're here, thank you.
الرئيس كلينتون , إذا كنت معنا هنا , شكرا لك .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
So the question is, why are so many people so wrong
إذا السؤال هو : لماذا يخطيء أناس كثيرون
about something so important? I think there are a number of reasons.
حول موضوع مهم جدا مثل هذا ؟ أعتقد أن هناك أكثر من سبب لذلك .
One of them is we have better reporting. The Associated Press
أحدهم هو إننا نمتلك اليوم وسائل تغطية إعلامية أفضل : " الصحافة
is a better chronicler of wars over the surface of the Earth
أفضل مؤرخ إخباري للحروب على وجه الأرض
than sixteenth-century monks were.
أكثر حتى مما كان عليه رهبان القرن السادس عشر ."
There's a cognitive illusion. We cognitive psychologists know that the easier it is
هناك وهم إدراكي : نحن ندرك أن الأخصائيون النفسيون يعرفون بأنه كلما كان أسهل أن
to recall specific instances of something,
نسترجع حالة خاصة لشيء ما ,
the higher the probability that you assign to it.
كلما زادت إحتمالية أن تكمل المشوار معها .
Things that we read about in the paper with gory footage
أشياء نقرأ عنها في الجرائد مع صور دموية
burn into memory more than reports of a lot more people dying
ترّسخ في ذاكرتنا أكثر من أخبار موت الكثير من البشر
in their beds of old age. There are dynamics in the opinion
على فراشهم بسبب كبر السن . هناك ديناميكية في الرأي
and advocacy markets: no one ever attracted observers, advocates
وأسواق الناشطين : لم يستطيع أحد أن يغري المراقبين , الناشطين
and donors by saying
والمتبرعين ويقول
things just seem to be getting better and better.
" الأحداث تبدو أنها تتخذ وضع أفضل فأفضل . "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
There's guilt about our treatment of native peoples
هناك شهور بالذنب من معاملتنا للسكان الأصليين
in modern intellectual life, and an unwillingness to acknowledge
في الحياة الثقافية الحديثة , وعدم الرغبة في الإعتراف
there could be anything good about Western culture.
بأن هناك أي شيء جيد حول الحضارة الغربية .
And of course, our change in standards can outpace the change
و بالطبع , تغييرنا لمقاييسنا يمكنه أن يتطور ويتغير
in behavior. One of the reasons violence went down
في سلوكنا . واحد من الأسباب التي جعلت العنف ينخفض
is that people got sick of the carnage and cruelty in their time.
هو إن الناس سأمت من المذابح و القسوة خلال أيامهم .
That's a process that seems to be continuing,
وهذا التطور يبدو لي إنه مستمر ,
but if it outstrips behavior by the standards of the day,
لكن إذا تخطت مقاييسنا السلوكية في يومنا هذا ,
things always look more barbaric than they would have been
ستبدو دائما التصرفات أكثر بربرية أكثر مما
by historic standards. So today, we get exercised -- and rightly so --
تم إعتبارها في المقاييس التاريخية . لذلك اليوم , قد إختبرنا - و هذا شيء سليم --
if a handful of murderers get executed by lethal injection
لو أن بعض القتله يتم إعدامهم بحقنة مميته
in Texas after a 15-year appeal process. We don't consider
في تكساس بعد 15 سنة من الإستئناف القضائي . نحن لا نعتبر
that a couple of hundred years ago, they may have been burned
أنه منذ 200 سنة ماضية أن من الممكن أن يتم حرقهم
at the stake for criticizing the king after a trial
أحياء بسبب إنتقادهم الملك بعد محاكمة
that lasted 10 minutes, and indeed, that that would have been repeated
إستمرت 10 دقائق فقط -- و بالطبع , هذا الأمر يتكرر
over and over again. Today, we look at capital punishment
دائما باستمرار . اليوم نرى عقوبة الإعدام
as evidence of how low our behavior can sink,
كدليل على كيف أن سلوكنا ممكن أن يخفق ,
rather than how high our standards have risen.
بدلا من أن نرى كيف أن مقاييسنا قد إرتفعت لأعلي .
Well, why has violence declined? No one really knows,
حسناً , لماذا تناقص العنف ؟ لا أحد فعلا يعرف ,
but I have read four explanations, all of which, I think,
لكنني قرأت أربعة تفسيرات , و كلها , كما أعتقد ,
have some grain of plausibility. The first is, maybe
تحتوي على الكثير من الصحة . الأول هو : ربما
Thomas Hobbes got it right. He was the one who said
توماس هوبس أصاب الحقيقية . هو الذي قال
that life in a state of nature was "solitary, poor, nasty, brutish
إن الحياة في حالتها الطبيعة كانت " متوحدة , فقيرة , مقرفة , عنيفة
and short." Not because, he argued,
و قصيرة . " ليس بسبب , كما يزعم ,
humans have some primordial thirst for blood
لدى الناس نزعة لإراقة الدماء ,
or aggressive instinct or territorial imperative,
أو عنف فطري أو حتمية الوجودية
but because of the logic of anarchy. In a state of anarchy,
لكن بسبب التفكير الفوضوي . في حالة الفوضى السياسية
there's a constant temptation to invade your neighbors preemptively,
هناك دائماً رغبة دائمة لغزو جيرانك عنوة ,
before they invade you. More recently, Thomas Schelling
قبل أن يغزوك هم . وحديثاً توماس سشيللنج
gives the analogy of a homeowner who hears a rustling
يعطي قياس على أي مالك منزل عندما يسمع صوت غريب
in the basement. Being a good American, he has a pistol
في القبو . كونه أمريكي جيد , كان يملك مسدس
in the nightstand, pulls out his gun, and walks down the stairs.
في الليل , يسحب مسدسه , و ينزل السلم .
And what does he see but a burglar with a gun in his hand.
و ما يرآه ما هو إلا عبارة عن لص و بيده مسدس .
Now, each one of them is thinking,
كل واحد منهم يفكر ,
"I don't really want to kill that guy, but he's about to kill me.
" أنا لا أريد أن أقتل هذا الشخص , و لكنه سوف يقتلني حتماً .
Maybe I had better shoot him, before he shoots me,
ربما الأفضل لي أن أطلق عليه النار قبل أن يفعل هو ,
especially since, even if he doesn't want to kill me,
بالأخص , حتي لو أنه لا يريد أن يقتلني ,
he's probably worrying right now that I might kill him
فربما هو قلق الآن من إني قد أقتله
before he kills me." And so on.
قبل أن يقتلني . " و هكذا .
Hunter-gatherer peoples explicitly go through this train of thought,
هذا القطار من الأفكار يحمل في طياته إصطياد واضح للناس
and will often raid their neighbors out of fear of being raided first.
وغالبا ما يدفع الناس لأن يغيروا على الجيران خوفاً من التعرض للهجوم أولاً .
Now, one way of dealing with this problem is by deterrence.
الآن , أحد الطرق للتعامل مع هذه المشكلة هي عن طريق الردع :
You don't strike first, but you have a publicly announced policy
أنت لا تضرب النار أولا, و لكنكك ستعلن سياستك للجميع
that you will retaliate savagely if you are invaded.
بأنك سترد بقوة إذا حاول أحد الإعتداء عليك .
The only thing is that it's
الشيء الوحيد بهذه السياسة
liable to having its bluff called, and therefore can only work
إنها تحتمل أن تكون غير جادة , و نتيجة لذلك يمكنها فقط أن تعمل
if it's credible. To make it credible, you must avenge all insults
إذا كانت معززة . لجعل سياستك هذه مٌصدقة و قوية يجب أن تثأر من أي إهانة
and settle all scores, which leads to the cycles of bloody vendetta.
و تحقق بذلك النتائج المرجوة , و هو ما يمكن أن يؤدي إلى حلقة من الثأر الدموي .
Life becomes an episode of "The Sopranos." Hobbes' solution,
تصبح الحياة جزء من مسلسل من الإزعاج لا يحتمل . حل هوبس ,
the "Leviathan," was that if authority for the legitimate use
ال " تنين " , كان إذا إستعملت السلطات التشريعية
of violence was vested in a single democratic agency -- a leviathan --
العنف كحق إنتفاع في وحدة ديموقراطية واحدة -- التنين --
then such a state can reduce the temptation of attack,
عندها يمكن أن يكون في حالة تقلل من الرغبة في الإعتداء ,
because any kind of aggression will be punished,
لأن أي نوع من العدوانية سيتم معاقبتها ,
leaving its profitability as zero. That would remove the temptation
مما سيجعل العدوانية غير نافعه . هذا سيزيل الرغبة
to invade preemptively, out of fear of them attacking you first.
في أن تعاديهم قبل أن يعادونك لأنك تخاف من أن يهاجموك أولاً .
It removes the need for a hair trigger for retaliation
و يزيل الرغبة في الإحتياج لإظهار الرغبة السريعة في الإنتقام
to make your deterrent threat credible. And therefore, it would lead
ويجعل تهديدك كرادع تهديد حيقيقي . إذا , سيؤدي هذا
to a state of peace. Eisner -- the man who plotted the homicide rates
إلى حالة سلام . إسنر -- الرجل الذي سجل معدلات عمليات القتل
that you failed to see in the earlier slide --
الذين لم تستطيعوا أن تروها في أول العرض --
argued that the timing of the decline of homicide in Europe
يزعم بأن وقت إنحسار عمليات القتل في أوروبا
coincided with the rise of centralized states.
تزامن مع إرتفاع حالة حكم المركزية .
So that's a bit of a support for the leviathan theory.
وهذا جزء بسيط يدعم نظرية التنين .
Also supporting it is the fact that we today see eruptions of violence
أيضا يدعم حقيقة أننا نري اليوم إرتفاع للعنف
in zones of anarchy, in failed states, collapsed empires,
في مناطق إنعدام قوة الحكومة : في الدول الفاشلة , الإمبراطوريات المنهارة ,
frontier regions, mafias, street gangs and so on.
مناطق إنعدام الحدود , المافيا , عصابات الشوارع و غيرها .
The second explanation is that in many times and places,
التفسير الثاني هو أنه في كثير من الأوقات و الأماكن
there is a widespread sentiment that life is cheap.
أن هناك إنتشار لفكرة أن الحياة رخيصة .
In earlier times, when suffering and early death were common
في الأيام القديمة , عندما كانت المعاناة و الموت المبكر شيء مألوف
in one's own life, one has fewer compunctions about inflicting them
في حياة الفرد الخاصة , فرد يملك القليل أو إنعدام الشعور بالذنب بإنعكاسات إيمانه
on others. And as technology and economic efficiency make life
علي الأخرين . وبتأثير التكنولوجيا و دقة الإقتصاد التي جعلت الحياة
longer and more pleasant, one puts a higher value on life in general.
أطول و أكثر متعة , فرد يضع قيمة أعلي للحياة عموماَ .
This was an argument from the political scientist James Payne.
كان هذا جدال من العالم السياسي جيمس باين .
A third explanation invokes the concept of a nonzero-sum game,
التفسير الثالث يتطلب مفهوم " لعبة المجموع ألا- صفري , "
and was worked out in the book "Nonzero" by the journalist
وكانت تعمل جيداَ في كتاب لا- زيرو للصحفي
Robert Wright. Wright points out that in certain circumstances,
روبرت رايت . أشار رايت إلي أنه في بعض الظروف المعينة
cooperation or non-violence can benefit both parties
في العمل معاَ , التي تبعد عن العنف , أن تفيد كل من الطرفين
in an interaction, such as gains in trade when two parties trade
في تفاعل جيد , مثل تحقيق مكاسب تجارية عندما يتبادل طرفين
their surpluses and both come out ahead, or when two parties
صادراتهم و كل منهم منفتح علي الآخر , أو عندما
lay down their arms and split the so-called peace dividend
يتركون أسلحتهم جانباَ ويتشاركون فيما يسمي بالسلام المشترك
that results in them not having to fight the whole time.
الذي من جانبه أن يريحهم من شر الحرب علي مدار الزمن .
Wright argues that technology has increased the number
رايت زعم أن التكنولوجيا زادت من أعداد
of positive-sum games that humans tend to be embroiled in,
ومكاسب التعاملات الإيجابية بين البشر الذين إعتادوا أن يتعاملوا فيما بينهم
by allowing the trade of goods, services and ideas
بالسماح بالتبادلات التجارية للبضائع , الخدمات و الأفكار
over longer distances and among larger groups of people.
علي مسافات أبعد و بين مجموعات أكبر من الناس .
The result is that other people become more valuable alive than dead,
النتيجة هي أن الناس أصبحت تمثل قيمة أعلي وهم أحياء أكثر منهم أموات ,
and violence declines for selfish reasons. As Wright put it,
والعنف ينخفض لأسباب أنانية . كما وضعها رايت ,
"Among the many reasons that I think that we should not bomb
" التي من بين هذه الأسباب التي أعتقد إننا لم يكن مفروض أن نفجر
the Japanese is that they built my mini-van."
اليابانيين لإنهم قد بنوا سيارتي الميني-فان . "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
The fourth explanation is captured in the title of a book
التفسير الرابع موضح في عنوان كتاب
called "The Expanding Circle," by the philosopher Peter Singer,
المسمي ب الدائرة الموسّعة , للفيلسوف بيتر سينجر
who argues that evolution bequeathed humans with a sense
الذي يزعم أن تطور الإنسانية الموروثة بنوع
of empathy, an ability to treat other peoples' interests
من التعاطف : القدرة علي التعامل مع مصالح الشعوب الأخري
as comparable to one's own. Unfortunately, by default
كتقارب لمصلحة شعب واحد . لسوء الحظ , بإفتراض
we apply it only to a very narrow circle of friends and family.
إننا طبقنا ذلك فقط علي مجموعة مقربة جداً من الأصدقاء و العائلة .
People outside that circle are treated as sub-human,
الناس خارج تلك الدائرة يعاملون كبشر من درجة ثانية
and can be exploited with impunity. But, over history,
ويمكن أن يٌستغلوا بنوع من عدم التكافؤ . لكن مع التاريخ ,
the circle has expanded. One can see, in historical record,
الدائرة قد إتسعت . قد يري شخص ما , في السجلات التاريخية
it expanding from the village, to the clan, to the tribe,
الإتساع من القرية , للعشيرة , للقبيلة ,
to the nation, to other races, to both sexes,
للأمة , لنوع البشر , لكل من نوعي البشرية الرجل و المرأة
and, in Singer's own arguments, something that we should extend
وفي , زعم سينجر , هناك شيئ لابد من إضافته
to other sentient species. The question is,
للمجموعات الاخري لإكتمال الصورة . السؤال هو ,
if this has happened, what has powered that expansion?
إذا حدث ذلك بالفعل , ما الذي فعّل ذلك التوسّع في الأولويات ؟
And there are a number of possibilities, such as increasing circles
وهناك الكثير من الإحتمالات . بإتساع دوائر
of reciprocity in the sense that Robert Wright argues for.
الناس التي تتفق مع بعضها البعض علي زعم روبرت رايت .
The logic of the golden rule -- the more you think about and interact
منطق القاعدة الذهبية : كلما تفكر بها وتتفاعل
with other people, the more you realize that it is untenable
مع الناس الآخرين كلما تدرك أنه من المتعذر إن لم يكن مستحيل
to privilege your interests over theirs,
لتحقيق مصالحك معهم ,
at least not if you want them to listen to you. You can't say
علي الأقل إذا أردتهم أن يستمعوا إليك . لا تستطيع أن تقول
that my interests are special compared to yours,
أن مصالحي خاصة بالمقارنة إلي مصالحك ,
anymore than you can say that the particular spot
أكثر من إنك تستطيع أن تقول أن النقطة المحددة
that I'm standing on is a unique part of the universe
التي أقف فيها علي وجه الخصوص هي نقطة متفردة من الكون
because I happen to be standing on it that very minute.
لأنني حدث وأنا أقف عليها فترة زمنية .
It may also be powered by cosmopolitanism, by histories,
إنها من الممكن أن تدعم باللاقومية التي هي عكس الوطنية : بالتاريخ
and journalism, and memoirs, and realistic fiction, and travel,
والصحافة و المذكرات والخيال الواقعي و السفر
and literacy, which allows you to project yourself into the lives
والفكر , الذي يسمح لك للتغلغل في حياة
of other people that formerly you may have treated as sub-human,
الناس الأخرين الذي إعتدت أن تعاملهم في الماضي كإحتياطي أو كدرجة ثانية ,
and also to realize the accidental contingency of your own station
وأيضا لتدرك الطوارئ العارضة لموقفك الخاص
in life, the sense that "there but for fortune go I."
في الحياة ; بمعني أن " هناك فرص للمستقبل تجعلني مستعد لأن أذهب هناك "
Whatever its causes, the decline of violence, I think,
مهما كانت الأسباب , إن إنخفاض العنف
has profound implications. It should force us to ask not just, why
له إسقاطات عميقة . إنه لابد أن يجبرنا أن نسأل ليس فقط " لماذا
is there war? But also, why is there peace? Not just,
هناك حرب ؟ " لكن أيضا " لماذا هناك سلام ؟ " ليس فقط
what are we doing wrong? But also, what have we been doing right?
" ما الخطأ الذي نفعله ؟ " لكن أيضا " ما الصواب الذي كنا ومازلنا نفعله ؟ "
Because we have been doing something right,
لأننا كنا ومازلنا نفعل شيئاَ صواباَ ,
and it sure would be good to find out what it is.
وبألتأكيد سيكون من الجيد أن نعرف ما هو .
Thank you very much.
أشكركم كثيراَ .
(Applause).
( تصفيق )
Chris Anderson: I loved that talk. I think a lot of people here in the room would say
كريس آندرسون : أحببت هذا الحديث . أنا أعتقد أن كثير من الناس في هذه الغرفة سيقولون
that that expansion of -- that you were talking about,
أن ذلك التوسع -- الذي كنتم تتحدثون عنه ,
that Peter Singer talks about, is also driven by, just by technology,
أن حديث بيتر سينجر , هو أيضاَ مَدفوع من, فقط بالتكنولوجيا ,
by greater visibility of the other, and the sense that the world
برؤية أعمق للآخر , ومن مٌنطلق أن العالم
is therefore getting smaller. I mean, is that also a grain of truth?
أصبح صغيراَ جدا . أقصد , هل هناك أي أثر للحقيقة هنا ؟
Steven Pinker: Very much. It would fit both in Wright's theory,
ستيفن بينكر : بالتأكيد . إنه مطابق لحديثهما في نظرية رايت ,
that it allows us to enjoy the benefits of cooperation
التي تسمح لنا أن نستمتع بفوائد التعاون
over larger and larger circles. But also, I think it helps us
علي نطاق دوائر كبيرة وكثيرة . لكن أيضاَ , أنا أعتقد إنها تساعدنا
imagine what it's like to be someone else. I think when you read
أن نتخيل أو بمعني أن نحس بشخص آخر . أنا أعتقد إنه عندما تقرأون
these horrific tortures that were common in the Middle Ages, you think,
هذا التعذيب البشع الذي كان شائعا في العصور الوسطي فتفكر ,
how could they possibly have done it,
كيف إستطاعوا أن يفعلوها ,
how could they have not have empathized with the person
كيف لم يكن هناك أي نوع من التعاطف مع ذلك الشخص
that they're disemboweling? But clearly,
الذي يعذبونه ؟ لكن من الواضح ,
as far as they're concerned, this is just an alien being
بقدر ما يشعرون بالقلق , هذا لا يتعدي كونه وحش غريب
that does not have feelings akin to their own. Anything, I think,
ليس له أية مشاعر مماثلة للتي يكنها لمجموعته . علي أي حال , أنا أعتقد ,
that makes it easier to imagine trading places
أنه يجعلنا من السهوله أن نتخيل أماكن تبادٌلية
with someone else means that it increases your moral consideration
مع شخص آخر ستعمل علي زيادة تقييمكم وفِكرتكم عن
to that other person.
ذلك الشخص .
CA: Well, Steve, I would love every news media owner to hear that talk
كريس آندرسون : حسناَ , ستيفن , أنا أتمني أن يسمع هذا الحديث كل مالك لقناة إخبارية
at some point in the next year. I think it's really important. Thank you so much.
في وقت ما بحلول العام القادم . أنا أعتقد إنه هام للغاية . أشكرك كثيراَ .
SP: My pleasure.
ستيفن بينكر : لي الشرف